Hi guys.
Welcome back.
Now if anything which is very important I mean at BOT of communication for effective project management
then that is Monda and control project.
This is vital for the success of any project as a project manager.
You can see that most of the time the person 90 percent of your time would go into activities one would
be communication on this communication will mean communicating with anybody and everybody.
And then you have monitor and control project well you're going to track review and approved the project
to all the stakeholders the sponsors.
Everybody does vital activities.
Remember this is very important for your effective project management because most of the projects I
mean I cannot think of any project which is kind of static.
Most of the project in todays world are dynamic you will encounter new challenges every day.
Sometimes a resource will go on emergency leave.
Sometimes you are expecting some kind of input as deliverable and then you or your deliverables were
depending on that.
But you were the other party failed to deliver that and now your work is hanging.
So project is very dynamic and you can never imagine in fact you can never imagine all the ways you
know things can go wrong in the project and resources logistical issues funding.
I mean you are a project manager but you may realize that the stakeholders fail to give some kind of
requirement.
Now halfway down they may decide to put that requirement that functionality as a number one priority.
Now you are supposed to deliver that.
But there is no funding there is no time and you have to juggle all the resources you have to make sure
that it is delivered.
So that is why its very important to keep track of all the issues.
Major Minor and deport them because if something goes wrong at a human nature a lot of time people are
trying to find a scapegoat and project managers are the favorite ones so if something goes wrong they
will love to put it on you.
They will not say that they are not compromising with the budget or time line or they will not proactively
giving requirements.
They will simply say that it was your job to track and report if it was going to back to you.
So its very important to make sure that you track and report these things.
And as I mentioned in the slide I mean if you identify something early you can report it to the stakeholders
and get the remedies or whatever need to return to handle that.
And it is performed throughout the project till the project is delivered.
You cannot relax.
You have to be on your toes monitoring and tracking everything.
This is the end product diagram and as you can imagine all components of project plan are in put and
all the project documents.
We have a assumption log and ASM log is very important in project management because as I mentioned
your deliverables may depend upon something else.
Now that is your assumption.
And if that assumption goes wrong.
It can really impact your deliverables.
So it has to be there in the assumption log and the risk factors because your stakeholders need to know.
Because ultimately I mean there are third party applications you are working with those teams are not
reporting to you.
Even if you follow up with them at times you may not get the desire to list them or take their own sweet
time.
So its very important to go and support all the stakeholders so that they can follow up with those teams.
Basic self-esteem which basically the first two emerge.
So when you make your demands you identify the changes assumptions risk factors all of that.
And within those estimates you put all that information in fact is a separate document itself.
Admission can be a separate document itself but there's no standard template.
A lot of companies use different kind of numbers could be a simple word document.
You know you may simply export the change request and then add a few more columns and the changes which
will be required in your system.
And then you simply put the cost.
So whatever piece this was used to put that cost let's say you said that a new service will be needed
will be developed to deliver that change.
Now that is the basis for your estimation.
And now let's say there's a variance in the requirements.
The stakeholders are asking you to develop something else.
If you are tracking your project activities you can simply notice the concern that this was your initial
basis for this admission.
And if you're deviating from that how that is going to impact the project sometimes let's say initially
is to move forward towards higher side.
And now you know that requirement is not that big.
So you might even end up with the positive impact that is the current data for schools down.
But in some cases in fact in many cases you will also get cases when the estimates will go up.
So this is of estimation is that and it is very important as input for monitoring and tracking the project
cost forecasting is a standard procedure used by many companies in their technology division.
In fact in many the divisions basically it's like you know having confidence limit based on the past
experience that and you evaluate the performance of current project could determine if this project
is going within that range within that tolerance limit.
So it's very important to make sure that we don't all spend on the projects and this cost for costing
helps in that an issue can be anything I mean can be added EastEnder defects which are created for a
project and they also referred to as buds using tools like Espey called deacon to Lord Jesus or some
other tools or any you know assumptions of this fact.
So it should basically represent that list and who is responsible for that which are open and the closed
and who's responsible for the open issues for most of the projects who will have these defects and which
are raised as the testing progresses.
And so we've been open these defects and they will assign them to the concerned team members that will
be part of your really should log.
But not just defect.
Remember that it can also include other stuff like these factors and the usual suspect lesson learned
registers Mindstorm list is basically a list of the important dates like you know if you are following.
Alexis grum you will have important dates for the springs various aspirins the start date and date important
meetings.
If you are using waterfall you will have the design phase for let's say on X Y Z date you'll start the
B R D preparation than it will on another date then the detail is and the solution document will be
started it will and then the development will start and so on.
So all of that project is scalable is part of your milestone date and it is used as input in case of
tracking because it's very important to compare these dudes and make sure that we stay on the track
if we are already late.
And if you were expected to deliver let's say a B R D then we need to know how we are going to compensate
for the last time.
So milestone are very very important for project tracking.
It's all about the X and quality report basically addresses the issues defects.
So as a man as I mentioned earlier in case of issues that could be defects and other issues here we
are specifically talking about the defects and the report on how to handle them it could be recommendations
Secuity.
And you know I'll work on these reports.
Could these reports that there's a pattern about the defect and and what can be done to reduce those
kind of diverse things like that this goodis to basically a list of person or of do's that have occurred
so far in the project and this report is basically information on the overall project risk as well as
an information on some unspecified individual risks so you can see that your project is green if it
is you know meeting all those deadlines and those milestone.
But if it crosses that particular timeframe but is within some kind of range let's say less than 25
percent and deviation then maybe it's yellow.
But if it crosses that burn deep ocean and goes above the tolerance limit then it could become red.
So that is your risk status on the oldest status and it can have individual specific items like I was
talking about that you know dependencies some dependency is not being delivered.
That is part of your risk report and then we have a similar forecast for skiddoo like cost where we
use tolerance.
And based on the past performance as input for the current project and then we have our performance
information and agreements enterprise in lamina factors organizational processes asserts and just a
note on performance information.
Basically this is you know this deal with all those performance metrics so let's see if we are talking
about funding now let's say the overall fund or our budget is hundert key and we have spent eighty thousand
dollars out of that.
But the project of progress is only 20 percent so that's low performance.
But if we have spent 80000 but the project progress is 90 or 100 percent then that's a good performance.
So you have to use these metrics which are very specific to project funding is very generally applicable
for all the projects.
Let's say you are talking about a website.
Now we have you know website load time many visit a website of uptight take certain seconds to load.
Let's say Google dot com when you type it in your browser it takes some time to load.
Now that is compared with the past performance expected data.
And then you design of a performance and then the metrics would be no page load time.
So you come up with these metrics compare them and look at the performance.
It's very important to compare and you know find out the performance data.
Because nowadays most of the corporates are very particular about the performance.
In fact they should be no matter what you do even if you deliver the project bartended.
But let's say took five times more bizarre than a standard regular project.
It's not verkaik.
So everything with it happens within the context and performance provide that context in terms of you
know comparing our current data.
And then we have tools and techniques.
So we have expert Jesmond data analysis and data analysis.
We have alternative analysis cost benefit analysis and value analysis root cause analysis and analysis
variance analysis.
So the analysis is basically used to select the corrective actions or a combination of corrective and
punitive actions to implement when a deviation occurs.
So let's say I took the example of that sort of vis a vis we were planning to implement that project
now let's say we don't need that service.
So we need to you know we will take certain actions to prevent any downfall or corrective actions to
you know to mitigate the risk.
So you will perform our DNA analysis to find those proven different corrective actions than we have
cost benefit analysis.
So if we are doing something if we're making any change in the bill we will need to perform this cost
benefit analysis to know if that changes verdict.
So this analysis is done for that.
Then we have our own value analysis.
It's basically an integrated perspective on scoops schedule and cost performance.
And then we have the cost analysis to basically as their terms suggest you are trying to identify the
root cause of the issue if something happened.
What was the trigger.
What was the cause of that event.
Because if we don't address the root cause the actual cause of the event that even that problem will
persist.
So it's very important to focus on the root cause and a trend analysis very important nowadays with
all that data analysis that are signs.
It's very important to understand the existing data and then come up with some kind of forecast based
on the performance based on past years and so trend analysis is basically that based on that you come
up with.
You try to identify the issues which can happen with the project and try to address them in advance
and variance analysis is basically identifying and analyzing the V and so between the actual and the
expected value.
So let's say you've expected your estimated cost Avaaz hundred thousand dollars but you spent 125.
So that is and there's a variance after 5000.
So you will perform variance analysis on that.
This helps you in you know identifying the women doing corrective actions and then we have the decision
making and of course the meetings you have to be you know meet the stakeholders.
And now meetings are not just face to face.
It can happen and they know telephones or Skype.
There are so many metrics and means so meetings with people all the stakeholders and all these kind
of techniques like meetings and decision making.
They go together.
I mean you will have a meeting where you will have all the considered stakeholders and then you're going
to play a decision making like voting and to see their votes and see if something should be promoted
to the production or not.
And then you have the output in the form of performance report so you will have performed date change.
First project management plan and document the cost for cost issue log.
Lesson learned or just this just this could do for cost.
So all of these are very important because all of them play a vital role in project management and these
are the applications of monitor and control project for them.
You can see that we are playing it everywhere and degree to change control managing team communication
risk project management plan project documents EFCA basically extend an environmental factors is organizational
process asserts
validate scoup and Torahs go controlling skiddoo cost quality resources monitoring communication risk
and controlling the procurement money to monitor stakeholder engagement.
You can see that it has got vinery of application it's very important.
As I mentioned earlier it's one of the core activities you are going to perform as project manager.
So that's it for now in the next video.
We'll continue with integrated chinch control.
Thank you.